<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Passion on cekrem.github.io</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/tags/passion/</link><description>Recent content in Passion on cekrem.github.io</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cekrem.github.io/tags/passion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Craftsman Mindset: Lessons from Four Weeks Offline</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/craftsman-mindset/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/craftsman-mindset/</guid><description>&lt;p>I just returned from four weeks of vacation—no laptop, no programming books, and a phone that could barely do more than call and text. It’s the longest I’ve been away from code in years. I didn’t plan to make it a digital detox, but it turned out to be exactly what I needed. If you do get a chance to do the same, I&amp;rsquo;d highly recommend it!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There’s something clarifying about stepping away from the things that usually fill your days. For me, that meant no late-night debugging, no “just one more chapter” of a programming book, and no side projects. Instead, I spent my sitting-down time reading more fiction, playing more Zelda, and generally letting my mind wander more than usual. It was good.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Passion</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/passion/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/passion/</guid><description>&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s Friday, and I&amp;rsquo;m up at 4am, wide awake, head filled with thoughts on recursive data structures and how to efficiently deal with them in our client&amp;rsquo;s Elm application. I tried going back to sleep for a few minutes, but decided against it. My (Garmin) sleep score averages well above 90%, so I can deal with one slightly short night. &lt;em>If I can just solve this puzzle&lt;/em>, it&amp;rsquo;ll be more than worth it! I&amp;rsquo;m doing test driven development on this particular problem. Not because I want to be fancy or make a point, but out of necessity – the complexity is far beyond what I would entrust myself without some guard rails while I iterate on it. &lt;strong>It feels great&lt;/strong>, and I&amp;rsquo;m already looking forward to the Sabbath moment when I can behold the work of my hands and see that it was good.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>