<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Dumbphone on cekrem.github.io</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/tags/dumbphone/</link><description>Recent content in Dumbphone on cekrem.github.io</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2024 13:35:45 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cekrem.github.io/tags/dumbphone/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Free at last – dumbing down my iPhone and disabling all evil!</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/dumbing-down-my-iphone/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2024 13:35:45 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/dumbing-down-my-iphone/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-problem">The problem&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>TL;DR: I need a phone, for a couple of obvious reasons. What I &lt;em>don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em> want is a smart phone killing my brain and soul, constantly bashing at my presence and peace of mind. Needless to say I&amp;rsquo;ve tried countless options and variations, but all my attempts have been less than ideal. My attempts usually fail in one of three ways:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Either it&amp;rsquo;s too limiting, like using a dumbphone or &lt;a href="https://cekrem.github.io/posts/why-im-not-using-the-lightphone-ii/">Lightphone II&lt;/a> 24/7, leaving me helpless when I need to pay for parking – or if someone sends me a long text&amp;hellip;,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Not limiting enough, like using some screen time whatever setting that I can easily override when I have a &lt;del>good&lt;/del> bad reason,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Too much hassle! Like using twin SIMs and changing device based on need/situation. Ah, the mental overhead involved in picking the right device for the occasion is massive, like choosing tie color 5 times every single day. Not that I ever wear ties. Also, things get out of sync (unanswered calls, texts etc) – it&amp;rsquo;s a mess.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="what-do-i-needwant-from-my-phone">What do I need/want from my phone?&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="must-haves">Must haves&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Working calls with sufficient coverage and audio quality. Also, bluetooth!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Texts! I love the iMessage protocol (with MMS fallback), but anything supporting long texts is fine.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A Camera. I thought I didn&amp;rsquo;t need this, and usually I really don&amp;rsquo;t. But sometimes, not having a camera at hand really sucks. Seems like the Lightphone guys came to the same conclusion seeing as the &lt;a href="https://www.thelightphone.com/shop/products/light-phone-iii?ref=lightphone-ii">Lightphone III&lt;/a> features a quite nice one!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The ability to &lt;em>completely disable&lt;/em> All Evil™ from the phone&lt;/strong>, whether things being actively intrusive or distracting (like unwanted notifications), or just &amp;ldquo;open doors&amp;rdquo; to self imposed rabbit holes of time wasting and brain micro-waving. The hardest one to kill of is actually the built in browser. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t help much to delete the Gmail app as long as I can just gmail.com my way back anyway.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Going by this list alone, I guess The &lt;a href="https://www.thelightphone.com/shop/products/light-phone-iii?ref=lightphone-ii">Lightphone III&lt;/a> could be a viable option. But it&amp;rsquo;s a bit expensive, and I already have an expensive phone. And there&amp;rsquo;s my second list as well:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Why I'm not using the Lightphone II (but my daughter is)</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/why-im-not-using-the-lightphone-ii/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2022 11:09:30 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/why-im-not-using-the-lightphone-ii/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="whats-a-light-phone-and-why-are-there-two-of-them">What&amp;rsquo;s a Light Phone, and why are there two of them?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The original Light Phone was a seriously dumb device. No texting, only phone calls. The company behind it never meant for it to be your only device, but a device to bring when you were &amp;ldquo;going light&amp;rdquo; – detaching yourself from all the digital clutter of your everyday (social media, feeds, notifications ++). It was a big a hit as one might expect, I guess, but quite a few people found the experience delightfully refreshing – but definitely not sustainable. After all, we need a few more bare essentials than just phone calls. Right?&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>