<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Tools on cekrem.github.io</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/tags/tools/</link><description>Recent content in Tools on cekrem.github.io</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cekrem.github.io/tags/tools/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Claude Code: Game Changer or Just Hype?</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/claude-code-game-changer-or-just-hype/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/claude-code-game-changer-or-just-hype/</guid><description>&lt;p>Last week, I watched two very different developers encounter Claude Code for the first time. The contrast in their reactions perfectly captures the tension I&amp;rsquo;ve been feeling about AI coding assistants lately.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For those unfamiliar, &lt;a href="https://www.anthropic.com/claude-code" class="external-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Claude Code&lt;/a> is Anthropic&amp;rsquo;s AI-powered coding assistant that can read, write, and edit code across your entire codebase. Unlike traditional autocomplete tools, it can understand context across multiple files, execute commands, run tests, and even browse the web for documentation. Think of it as having an AI pair programmer that never gets tired and has read every Stack Overflow answer ever written.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Feedback.one: A Refreshing Take on User Feedback Built with Elm and Rust</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/feedback-one-elm-rust-feedback-widget/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/feedback-one-elm-rust-feedback-widget/</guid><description>&lt;p>I recently added a new feedback widget to this site – &lt;a href="https://feedback.one/" class="external-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Feedback.one&lt;/a> – and I&amp;rsquo;m impressed enough with it that I thought it deserved its own post. Beyond being a useful tool, it&amp;rsquo;s also an excellent example of how functional programming languages like Elm can shine in production environments.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-feedbackone">
 What is Feedback.one?
 &lt;a class="heading-link" href="#what-is-feedbackone">
 &lt;i class="fa-solid fa-link" aria-hidden="true" title="Link to heading">&lt;/i>
 &lt;span class="sr-only">Link to heading&lt;/span>
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>At its core, Feedback.one is a simple but powerful tool that adds a non-intrusive feedback button to your website. With one line of code, you get:&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>