<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>cekrem.github.io</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on cekrem.github.io</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cekrem.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>React Advent Calendar – keto vegan, gluten free and no parabens or plastic wrapping</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/react-advent-calendar/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/react-advent-calendar/</guid><description>TL;DR: I made an advent calendar in React, my wife loved it I grew up with a lot of creative advent calendars. The one type I didn&amp;rsquo;t get was the standard chocolate one that&amp;rsquo;s most common these days. While I&amp;rsquo;ve not consistently been very good at paying this forward, I do make an effort some years to do something a bit different for my wife. Yes, my wife; the kids get standard ones :P This year&amp;rsquo;s plan was simple: create an online calendar with cozy favors, encouragements and the like each day until Christmas.</description></item><item><title>create-elm-live-app – the smallest npm package ever?</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/create-elm-live-app/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/create-elm-live-app/</guid><description>The problem I&amp;rsquo;ve been tinkering a bit with Elm lately. The super-enforced functional and minimal paradigm is very refreshing, and serves as a sort of detox after spending one too many hour stuck in Android&amp;rsquo;s not-so-lovely XML + mutating class world. Setting up a new bare minimum Elm app should be quite simple, but it turns out that there are a few more steps required than one would expect.</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/about/</guid><description>What floats my boat Following Jesus Best. Wife. Ever. Raising three incredible giant killers I also like Telling stories in a creative way (AKA working in tech) Music! Particularly playing drums or the guitar &amp;lt;3 Super Smash Bros Top three values as a software engineer Integrity Creativity Excellence</description></item><item><title>Development plan 2021-2023</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/devplan/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/devplan/</guid><description>What follows is my own personal development plan as a software engineer at Vipps. Some terms and expressions are a bit internal, as they will no doubt be for you as well on your own plan (should you find yourself inspired to write one), but I&amp;rsquo;ll leave it as is. Enjoy!
Context I&amp;rsquo;ve been at Vipps since 2018, mostly doing work that now belongs in the &amp;ldquo;Merchant Core&amp;rdquo; team.</description></item><item><title>pretty-git-report – a CLI to give you daily commit metrics</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/git-report/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/git-report/</guid><description>Have you ever&amp;hellip; Wanted to track your daily additions and deletions without leaving your beloved terminal? Busted your back piping git log {insert-hundred-flags} through endless hoops trying to create a somewhat human readable and useful output? Wanted to use a functional node.js cli with an immoral amount of Rambda usage? (Sorry about that, btw, I just wanted to see how far I could go. Quite far, it turns out!</description></item></channel></rss>