<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>vipps on cekrem.github.io</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/tags/vipps/</link><description>Recent content in vipps on cekrem.github.io</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cekrem.github.io/tags/vipps/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The End of an Era!</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/the-end-of-an-era/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/the-end-of-an-era/</guid><description>The Day Has Come. I&amp;rsquo;m officially archiving my previous development plan and moving on to new adventures in Vipps Mobile Pay! It&amp;rsquo;s been a long time coming, and I&amp;rsquo;m happy to say that I&amp;rsquo;ve achieved most of the goals I set out to achieve. I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a lot, and I&amp;rsquo;m ready to proceed towards the next chapter. I&amp;rsquo;m not, however, ready to make a new plan just yet. So consider this post ceremonial more than anything.</description></item><item><title>Development plan 2021-2023</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/devplan/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/devplan/</guid><description>Update: This plan is now archived. See The End of an Era for details.
What follows is my own personal development plan as a software engineer at Vipps Vipps MobilePay. Some terms and expressions are a bit internal, as they will no doubt be for you as well on your own plan (should you find yourself inspired to write one), but I&amp;rsquo;ll leave it as is. Enjoy!
Context I&amp;rsquo;ve been at Vipps MobilePay since 2018, mostly doing work that now belongs in the &amp;ldquo;Merchant Core&amp;rdquo; team.</description></item><item><title>Changing Jobs Without Leaving Your Company</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/changing-jobs-without-leaving-your-company/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 07:00:15 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/changing-jobs-without-leaving-your-company/</guid><description>So you&amp;rsquo;ve been at your company for a couple of years. Your parents tell you to stick around for another five, but other people in tech - and your adventurous self - tell you it&amp;rsquo;s about time to learn something new. What if you could do both? The most common path to take in order to learn something new, advance your career, increase your salary or simply Change Things Up A Bit involves leaving your company for something else.</description></item><item><title>Reducing Android Build Times on Azure by 80% using a Virtual Machine Scale Set (VMSS)</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/reducing-android-build-times-on-azure-by-80/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 12:00:21 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/reducing-android-build-times-on-azure-by-80/</guid><description>A VMSS is, put as plainly as possible, a cluster of VMs that are scaled on-demand or manually.
Context The Vipps App – until recently – took about 45 minutes to build on A$ure Azure. With a weekly release schedule, that might not sound like a huge dealbreaker, but since we&amp;rsquo;re using a &amp;ldquo;feature branch&amp;rdquo; approach to how we do git (ie no develop branch; master should always be deployable-ish), we don&amp;rsquo;t allow merging anything to master without a successful cloud build.</description></item></channel></rss>