<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Elm on cekrem.github.io</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/tags/elm/</link><description>Recent content in Elm on cekrem.github.io</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cekrem.github.io/tags/elm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Use Case for Port Boundaries in Frontend Development</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/a-case-for-port-boundaries-in-frontend/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/a-case-for-port-boundaries-in-frontend/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the Elm ecosystem, the browser is treated like an I/O device. DOM events, JavaScript interop, and even network requests are kept outside the core logic. Rather than allowing side effects to permeate the codebase, Elm channels them through strictly typed boundaries known as &lt;em>ports&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This architectural stance is both radical and liberating. It allows you to build user interfaces where logic remains pure, testable, and robust, even as surrounding technologies evolve.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Introducing HTML Helpers for Elm</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/introducing-html-helpers-for-elm/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/introducing-html-helpers-for-elm/</guid><description>&lt;p>As I continue to build more Elm applications, I find myself creating small utility functions to overcome common pain points. I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of abstracting away repetitive patterns into reusable, well-named functions. Today, I&amp;rsquo;m happy to announce the release of my first public Elm package: &lt;a href="https://package.elm-lang.org/packages/cekrem/html-helpers/latest/">html-helpers&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="whats-the-problem">What&amp;rsquo;s the Problem?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Elm&amp;rsquo;s HTML API is quite straightforward - you create HTML elements as functions, pass them attributes and children, and compose them together. But a few cases come up repeatedly that can be awkward:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Building Better UI Components: Elm Ports with Web Components</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/elm-ports-with-web-components/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/elm-ports-with-web-components/</guid><description>&lt;p>One of the most common questions I get about Elm is: &amp;ldquo;How do I integrate it with existing JavaScript ecosystems?&amp;rdquo; While Elm&amp;rsquo;s isolation is a strength, real-world projects often require working with external libraries, APIs, or UI components. Doing incremental migration is also the recommended way to introduce Elm, and luckily there are may ways to accomplish this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Today, I&amp;rsquo;ll show you how to combine two powerful technologies:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Elm Ports&lt;/strong>: The official way to communicate between Elm and JavaScript&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Web Components&lt;/strong>: Standard, framework-agnostic UI components&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>This combination gives us the best of both worlds: Elm&amp;rsquo;s type safety and predictable architecture alongside the reusability and interoperability of Web Components. Let&amp;rsquo;s dive in!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Feedback.one: A Refreshing Take on User Feedback Built with Elm and Rust</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/feedback-one-elm-rust-feedback-widget/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/feedback-one-elm-rust-feedback-widget/</guid><description>&lt;p>I recently added a new feedback widget to this site – &lt;a href="https://feedback.one/">Feedback.one&lt;/a> – and I&amp;rsquo;m impressed enough with it that I thought it deserved its own post. Beyond being a useful tool, it&amp;rsquo;s also an excellent example of how functional programming languages like Elm can shine in production environments.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-feedbackone">What is Feedback.one?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>At its core, Feedback.one is a simple but powerful tool that adds a non-intrusive feedback button to your website. With one line of code, you get:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Why I Hope I Get to Write a Lot of Elm Code in 2025</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/why-i-hope-i-get-to-write-a-lot-of-elm-code-in-2025/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/why-i-hope-i-get-to-write-a-lot-of-elm-code-in-2025/</guid><description>&lt;p>In a world dominated by React, Vue, and Svelte, it might seem strange to highlight Elm – a niche language that has existed since 2012 but has had fewer releases since then than React has in a year. But right now, when frontend development is becoming increasingly complex, and clients are doing heavy lifting that previously belonged on the other side of an API call, it&amp;rsquo;s worth taking a closer look at what Elm does right.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>create-elm-live-app – the smallest npm package ever?</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/create-elm-live-app/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/create-elm-live-app/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-problem">The problem&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been tinkering a bit with Elm lately. The super-enforced functional and minimal paradigm is very refreshing, and serves as a sort of detox after spending one too many hour stuck in Android&amp;rsquo;s not-so-lovely XML + mutating class world. Setting up a new bare minimum Elm app should be quite simple, but it turns out that there are a few more steps required than one would expect. My first instinct – being a React guy – was to try &lt;code>yarn create elm-app&lt;/code> (or &lt;code>npx create-elm-app&lt;/code>), hoping it would do the Elm-equivalent of what &lt;code>create-react-app&lt;/code> does. Turns out, to my disappointment, that the end result leaves something to be desired. No proper live-reload out of the box, and a lot of the webpack stuff I was hoping to avoid completely with Elm. Yuck.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>