<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Craft on cekrem.github.io</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/tags/craft/</link><description>Recent content in Craft on cekrem.github.io</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cekrem.github.io/tags/craft/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Claude Code: Game Changer or Just Hype?</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/claude-code-game-changer-or-just-hype/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/claude-code-game-changer-or-just-hype/</guid><description>&lt;p>Last week, I watched two very different developers encounter Claude Code for the first time. The contrast in their reactions perfectly captures the tension I&amp;rsquo;ve been feeling about AI coding assistants lately.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My first friend - let&amp;rsquo;s call him the &amp;ldquo;Null Stack Developer&amp;rdquo; - is one of those brilliant &amp;ldquo;vibe coders&amp;rdquo; who can make anything work with enough caffeine and sheer determination. He fired up Claude Code, asked it to build him a React dashboard with real-time data visualization, and within minutes was marveling at the generated components. &amp;ldquo;This is insane,&amp;rdquo; he kept saying, watching perfectly structured TypeScript materialize on his screen. &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s like having a senior developer sitting next to me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Coding as Craft: Going Back to the Old Gym</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/coding-as-craft-going-back-to-the-old-gym/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/coding-as-craft-going-back-to-the-old-gym/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recently, &lt;a href="https://x.com/tobi/status/1909231499448401946" class="external-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Shopify&amp;rsquo;s CEO Tobi Lütke shared his thoughts on AI&amp;rsquo;s role in coding&lt;/a>, stating that &amp;ldquo;reflexive AI usage is now a baseline expectation at Shopify.&amp;rdquo; The gist of his message was that AI is revolutionizing how we work, and everybody should jump on board this train or risk being left behind. I&amp;rsquo;m paraphrasing a bit, but not much – check out the post for complete context and content.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This struck a chord with me, but not in the way he intended. In a Slack conversation with fellow Elm engineers, I found myself typing:&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>