<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Book on cekrem.github.io</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/tags/book/</link><description>Recent content in Book on cekrem.github.io</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cekrem.github.io/tags/book/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>An Elm Primer: The missing chapter on JavaScript interop</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/elm-book-missing-chapter-8-ports-interop/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/elm-book-missing-chapter-8-ports-interop/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been having a week off from working with my book, mainly to celebrate the initial completion of parts I and II (out of IV). But it turns out I had a slight &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt; connection error on my private Macbook after adding the last chapter so what I actually published was less than all of part II: chapter 8 on ports and javascript interop was missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This serves as a reminder that the outside world is not to be trusted, and that any interaction and side-effect can (and will, from time to time) fail – even something as ordinary as a &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt;. Which happens to be a major theme in the missing chapter, humbly presented to you below.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Elm is the Best Way for React Developers to Learn Real Functional Programming</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/elm-book-announcement/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/elm-book-announcement/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As my newsletter subscribers suspect and my Ensō colleagues already know by now, &lt;strong&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently started writing a book&lt;/strong&gt;. Not just any book—a practical guide for React developers who want to learn functional programming the right way, without getting lost in academic theory or Haskell&amp;rsquo;s notorious learning curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cekrem.github.io/images/book.png" alt="Placeholder book cover"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The working title is &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;An Elm Primer for React Developers: The Best Way to Learn Real Functional Programming&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;, and yes, that&amp;rsquo;s a bold claim. Let me explain why I believe it. (Or go right ahead and download a free sample / buy the book on its &lt;a href="https://leanpub.com/elm-for-react-devs" class="external-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;leanpub landing site&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>