<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Book on cekrem.github.io</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/tags/book/</link><description>Recent content in Book on cekrem.github.io</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cekrem.github.io/tags/book/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>An Elm Primer: Declarative Dialogs with MutationObserver</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/elm-book-declarative-dialogs-mutation-observer/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/elm-book-declarative-dialogs-mutation-observer/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a small problem that says something bigger about Elm&amp;rsquo;s architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HTML&amp;rsquo;s native &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;dialog&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; element is genuinely useful. You get proper focus trapping, the Escape key works automatically, backdrop handling is built in. But there&amp;rsquo;s a catch: to open a dialog as a modal, you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to call &lt;code&gt;dialog.showModal()&lt;/code&gt;. There&amp;rsquo;s no HTML attribute for &amp;ldquo;make this a modal.&amp;rdquo; It&amp;rsquo;s imperative all the way down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what happens when your entire view layer is a pure function of state?&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Organizing Files and Modules in Elm: Building an Advent Calendar</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/elm-book-chapter-9-organizing-files-and-modules/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/elm-book-chapter-9-organizing-files-and-modules/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re officially in Part III of the book now, where we shift from systematic concept exploration to building real applications. This chapter asks you to unlearn something you probably picked up from years of JavaScript development: the instinct to split code into multiple files at arbitrary line counts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual, &lt;a href="https://leanpub.com/elm-for-react-devs" class="external-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;the book can be found and bought @ leanpub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(And as usual, the formatting is slightly more adequate in the actual book than on this Hugo blog, but we&amp;rsquo;ll make do.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>An Elm Primer: The missing chapter on JavaScript interop</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/elm-book-missing-chapter-8-ports-interop/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/elm-book-missing-chapter-8-ports-interop/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been having a week off from working with my book, mainly to celebrate the initial completion of parts I and II (out of IV). But it turns out I had a slight &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt; connection error on my private Macbook after adding the last chapter so what I actually published was less than all of part II: chapter 8 on ports and javascript interop was missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This serves as a reminder that the outside world is not to be trusted, and that any interaction and side-effect can (and will, from time to time) fail – even something as ordinary as a &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt;. Which happens to be a major theme in the missing chapter, humbly presented to you below.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Elm is the Best Way for React Developers to Learn Real Functional Programming</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/elm-book-announcement/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/elm-book-announcement/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As my newsletter subscribers suspect and my Ensō colleagues already know by now, &lt;strong&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently started writing a book&lt;/strong&gt;. Not just any book—a practical guide for React developers who want to learn functional programming the right way, without getting lost in academic theory or Haskell&amp;rsquo;s notorious learning curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cekrem.github.io/images/book.png" alt="Placeholder book cover"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The working title is &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;An Elm Primer for React Developers: The Best Way to Learn Real Functional Programming&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;, and yes, that&amp;rsquo;s a bold claim. Let me explain why I believe it. (Or go right ahead and download a free sample / buy the book on its &lt;a href="https://leanpub.com/elm-for-react-devs" class="external-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;leanpub landing site&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>