<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on cekrem.github.io</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on cekrem.github.io</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cekrem.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Development plan 2021-2023</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/devplan/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/devplan/</guid><description>What follows is my own personal development plan as a software engineer at Vipps Vipps MobilePay. Some terms and expressions are a bit internal, as they will no doubt be for you as well on your own plan (should you find yourself inspired to write one), but I&amp;rsquo;ll leave it as is. Enjoy!
Context I&amp;rsquo;ve been at Vipps MobilePay since 2018, mostly doing work that now belongs in the &amp;ldquo;Merchant Core&amp;rdquo; team.</description></item><item><title>Why I'm not using the Lightphone II (but my daughter is)</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/why-im-not-using-the-lightphone-ii/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2022 11:09:30 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/why-im-not-using-the-lightphone-ii/</guid><description>What&amp;rsquo;s a Light Phone, and why are there two of them? The original Light Phone was a seriously dumb device. No texting, only phone calls. The company behind it never meant for it to be your only device, but a device to bring when you were &amp;ldquo;going light&amp;rdquo; – detaching yourself from all the digital clutter of your everyday (social media, feeds, notifications ++). It was a big a hit as one might expect, I guess, but quite a few people found the experience delightfully refreshing – but definitely not sustainable.</description></item><item><title>ripnote – the fastest and fuzziest way for a developer to take notes</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/ripnote/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2022 13:35:45 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/ripnote/</guid><description>The best tool for note-taking? The one you have close at hand. ReMarkable this, vintage inherited bio-dynamic paper that – it&amp;rsquo;ll do you no good what-so-ever if it&amp;rsquo;s not readily available when you need it. I&amp;rsquo;ve spent way too much time trying to find the &amp;ldquo;ideal&amp;rdquo; solution for keeping track of notes and ideas through my workday. But all I really need is this:
To jot down new notes and ideas fast!</description></item><item><title>Changing Jobs Without Leaving Your Company</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/changing-jobs-without-leaving-your-company/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 07:00:15 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/changing-jobs-without-leaving-your-company/</guid><description>So you&amp;rsquo;ve been at your company for a couple of years. Your parents tell you to stick around for another five, but other people in tech - and your adventurous self - tell you it&amp;rsquo;s about time to learn something new. What if you could do both? The most common path to take in order to learn something new, advance your career, increase your salary or simply Change Things Up A Bit involves leaving your company for something else.</description></item><item><title>Reducing Android Build Times on Azure by 80% using a Virtual Machine Scale Set (VMSS)</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/reducing-android-build-times-on-azure-by-80/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 12:00:21 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/reducing-android-build-times-on-azure-by-80/</guid><description>A VMSS is, put as plainly as possible, a cluster of VMs that are scaled on-demand or manually.
Context The Vipps App – until recently – took about 45 minutes to build on A$ure Azure. With a weekly release schedule, that might not sound like a huge dealbreaker, but since we&amp;rsquo;re using a &amp;ldquo;feature branch&amp;rdquo; approach to how we do git (ie no develop branch; master should always be deployable-ish), we don&amp;rsquo;t allow merging anything to master without a successful cloud build.</description></item><item><title>React Advent Calendar – keto vegan, gluten free and no parabens or plastic wrapping</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/react-advent-calendar/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/react-advent-calendar/</guid><description>TL;DR: I made an advent calendar in React, my wife loved it I grew up with a lot of creative advent calendars. The one type I didn&amp;rsquo;t get was the standard chocolate one that&amp;rsquo;s most common these days. While I&amp;rsquo;ve not consistently been very good at paying this forward, I do make an effort some years to do something a bit different for my wife. Yes, my wife; the kids get standard ones :P This year&amp;rsquo;s plan was simple: create an online calendar with cozy favors, encouragements and the like each day until Christmas.</description></item><item><title>create-elm-live-app – the smallest npm package ever?</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/create-elm-live-app/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/create-elm-live-app/</guid><description>The problem I&amp;rsquo;ve been tinkering a bit with Elm lately. The super-enforced functional and minimal paradigm is very refreshing, and serves as a sort of detox after spending one too many hour stuck in Android&amp;rsquo;s not-so-lovely XML + mutating class world. Setting up a new bare minimum Elm app should be quite simple, but it turns out that there are a few more steps required than one would expect. My first instinct – being a React guy – was to try yarn create elm-app (or npx create-elm-app), hoping it would do the Elm-equivalent of what create-react-app does.</description></item><item><title>pretty-git-report – a CLI to give you daily commit metrics</title><link>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/git-report/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cekrem.github.io/posts/git-report/</guid><description>Have you ever&amp;hellip; Wanted to track your daily additions and deletions without leaving your beloved terminal? Busted your back piping git log {insert-hundred-flags} through endless hoops trying to create a somewhat human readable and useful output? Wanted to use a functional node.js cli with an immoral amount of Rambda usage? (Sorry about that, btw, I just wanted to see how far I could go. Quite far, it turns out!) Wished you would live to see a tool (any tool at all) that treverses a directory tree - :O – concurrently?</description></item></channel></rss>